Guide to the Aleksander Wat Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Aleksander Wat papers
1915-1988
GEN MSS 705
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
22.83
(48 boxes)
The papers document the life and writings of Aleksander Wat, from his early poetry in the 1910s to the posthumous publication of his work by his wife Paulina and by Czesław Miłosz. Early material (prior to the end of the Second World War) is sparse and consists chiefly of correspondence, personal documents and photographs. Among the early material is documentation of the Wat's exile in Kazakhstan. Later material includes numerous notebooks that contain drafts of poetry and prose writings, and the audio recordings that formed the basis for his memoir Mój wiek. The papers are of interest not only to researchers studying Wat's creative process and the context of his life, but also twentieth-century Polish literature, the relationship of authors to Soviet society, and the postwar Eastern European émigré literary community in France. Wat's repeated arrests and exile are documented in his notebooks, in personal papers, and in material related to his memoirs. His relationship to the émigré circle centered around the monthly Kultura in France is documented in correspondence with Jerzy Giedroyć, Gustaw Herling-Grudziński, Konstanty Jeleński, and Zygmunt Hertz. The posthumous success of his writings is documented in Paulina Wat's Correspondence in Series I, and in posthumously-dated material in the Writings series, which chiefly relates to the editing, translating, and publishing work of Paulina Wat and Czesław Miłosz.
Wat, Aleksander, 1900-1967
Miłosz, Czesław, 1911-2004
Watowa, Ola, 1903-1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Paulina Wat on the Edwin J. and Frederick W. Beinecke Rare Book Fund, 1988.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies and access copies of sound recordings for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1940-1985. II. Writings, 1942-1982. III. Personal Papers and Memorabilia, 1915-1985. IV. Writings of Others, 1921-1988. V. Printed Material, 1920-1978.
Aleksander Wat, 1900-1967
Aleksander Wat, poet, translator, critic, and co-founder of the Polish Futurism movement, was born Aleksander Chwat in 1900 in Warsaw, Poland. His early volumes of poetry include JA z jednej strony i JA z drugiej strony mego mopsożelaznego piecyka ( ME from One Side and ME from the Other Side of My Pug Iron Stove, 1920) and Bezrobotny Lucyfer ( Lucifer Unemployed, 1927). Wat's career was thwarted for decades during the Second World War and the Soviet era, as he was repeatedly imprisoned for political reasons and, with his wife Paulina (Ola Watowa) and son Andrzej, exiled to Kazakhstan. From the 1950s on, he suffered from a debilitating neurological illness (diagnosed as Wallenberg's syndrome) that also significantly impeded his writing. In 1959 he emigrated to France, where he lived until his suicide in 1967. In 1963-1964 he had a visiting appointment at the University of California, Berkeley, where he collaborated with Czesław Miłosz to record his memoirs. Wat continued to write prose and poetry in his later years. Much of this later writing was published posthumously, including Dziennik bez samogłosek ( Diary Without Vowels ) and Mój wiek ( My Century ), memoirs that recount his experience of twentieth-century Eastern European literary and political history.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the life and writings of Aleksander Wat, from his early poetry in the 1910s to the posthumous publication of his work by his wife Paulina (Ola Watowa) and by Czesław Miłosz. Early material (prior to the end of the Second World War) is sparse and consists chiefly of correspondence, personal documents and photographs. Among the early material is documentation of the Wat family's exile in Kazakhstan. Later material includes numerous notebooks that contain drafts of poetry and prose writings, and the audio recordings that formed the basis for Mój wiek. Two folders of lists and notes document the contents and organization of the material as it was received by the Beinecke Library are filed at the beginning of the collection.
The papers are of interest not only to researchers studying Wat's creative process and the context of his life, but also twentieth-century Polish literature, the relationship of authors to Soviet society, and the postwar Eastern European émigré literary community in France. Wat's repeated arrests and exile are documented in his notebooks, in personal papers, and in material related to his memoirs. His relationship to the émigré circle centered around the monthly Kultura in France is documented in correspondence with Jerzy Giedroyć, Gustaw Herling-Grudziński, Konstanty Jeleński, and Zygmunt Hertz. The posthumous success of his writings is documented in Paulina Wat's Correspondence in Series I, and in posthumously-dated material in the Writings series, which chiefly relates to the editing, translating, and publishing work of Paulina Wat and Czesław Miłosz.
Authors, Polish -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, Polish -- 20th Century; Polish literature -- 20th Century; Polish poetry -- 20th Century; Futurism (Literary movement) -- Poland; Emigration and immigration; Authors, Exiled -- Soviet Union; Poland -- History -- 1918-1945; Poland -- History -- 1945-1980; Poland -- Intellectual life -- 1918-1945; Poland -- Intellectual life -- 1945-1980; Poland -- Emigration and immigration; France -- Emigration and immigration; Audiovisual materials; Sound recordings; Notebooks; Photographs; Memoirs; Authors; Poets; Translators; Giedroyc, Jerzy, 1906-2000; Herling-Grudziński, Gustaw, 1919-2000; Hertz, Zygmunt, 1908-1979; Jeleński, Konstanty A. (Konstanty Aleksander), 1922-1987; Miłosz, Czesław, 1911-2004; Wat, Aleksander, 1900-1967; Watowa, Ola, 1903-1991
- Notes on the Papers by Paulina Wat and Others, undated
  Scope and Contents
  The notes filed under this heading reflect the organization of the papers as they were received by the Beinecke library. These notes may be helpful to researchers who are using references to the Aleksander Wat Papers dated prior to 2010.
  - List of contents, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Aleksander Wat's archive and work, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1940-1985; Series I; 4.17; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Aleksander Wat Correspondence and Paulina Wat Correspondence. Material is arranged alphabetically in each subseries.
  The earliest correspondence (1940-1946) relates chiefly to the Wat family's exile in Kazakhstan. The bulk of the correspondence dates from the late 1950s to 1967 and documents Aleksander Wat's emigration, editorial work and publication projects. Other correspondence, such as that with Wat's sister Seweryna Broniszówna and other family members, is of a more personal nature. Correspondence after 1967, as well as the Paulina Wat Correspondence, is chiefly related to the posthumous publication of Aleksander Wat's work. Correspondence is incoming, unless otherwise noted.
  - Aleksander Wat Correspondence
    - "A" General correspondence, 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Andrzejewski, Jerzy, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Askanas, Zdzisław, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Aveline, Claude, 1948-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "B" General correspondence, 1946-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Baliński, Stanisław, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - [Bandrowska?], Ewa, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Baraniecki, A., 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bednarczyk, Czesław, incoming and outgoing, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Behrens, Margaret, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bieńkowski, Zbigniew, 1955-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Błoński, Jan, 1961-1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bobba, _____, outgoing, 1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Brandys, Kazimierz and Maria, 1948-1957 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Breza, Tadeusz and Zofia, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Broniewski, Władysław, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Bronisz, _____, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Broniszówna, Seweryna, incoming and outgoing, 1945-1966 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    - Brzękowski, Jan, 1959-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - "C" General correspondence, 1947-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Caillois, Roger, 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Carl Hanser Verlag, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Caronia, Giuseppe, 1957-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Cazin, Paul, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Chadzyńska, Zofia, 1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Chwistkowa, Olga, 1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Ciołkosz, Adam and Lidia, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Le Contrat Social, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Craig, Gordon, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
      Includes photographs and printed material.
    - Cusack, Ralph, 1963-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Czachowska, Jadwiga, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Czapski, Józef, incoming and outgoing, 1956-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 38-43)
    - Czytelnik (Firm), 1946-1962 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - "D" General correspondence, 1947-1966 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Dąbrowska, Maria, 1960-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Daghani, Arnold, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Dedecius, Karl, incoming and outgoing, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Dialog, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Dryszkiewicz, Alicja, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Dubuis, Gisele, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - "E" General correspondence, 1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Eluard, Paul, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Emmanuel, Pierre, 1963-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Erlich, Wiktor, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - "F" General correspondence, 1946-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Fevrier, Paul, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - "G" General correspondence, 1947-1965 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Gałczyński, Natalia and Konstanty, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Gallant, Mavis, 1956-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 60-61)
    - Garcin, Raymond, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Giedroyć, Jerzy, inocming and outgoing, 1960-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 63-69)
    - Gömöri, George, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Gotlib, Henryk, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Grampp, Eileen, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Grossman, Gregory, 1964-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Grydzewski, Mieczysław, 1956-1967 (Box 2, Folder 74-76)
    - Grzybowska, Krystyna, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Grynsztein, Jakob, 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - "H" General correspondence, 1947-1963 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Hayward, Max, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Herbert, Zbigniew, 1966-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Herling-Grudziński, Gustaw, incoming and outgoing, 1957-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 82-88)
    - Hertz, Pawel, 1947-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Hertz, Zygmunt, incoming and outgoing, 1957-1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 90-99)
    - Heuyer, Georges, 1955-1959 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - "I" General correspondence, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Iłłakowiczówna, Kazimiera, 1954-1958 (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Institute for Study of the USSR, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - Instytut Badań Literackich, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Iwaniuk, Wacław, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - Iwaszkiewicz, Jarosław, incoming and outgoing (including copies), 1947-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 106-108)
    - "J" General correspondence, 1945-1964 (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - Jabłoński, Henryk, 1947-1960 (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - Jackson, Robert, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Jastrun, Mieczysław, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - Jeleńska, Teresa, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - Jeleński, Konstanty, 1958-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 114-120)
    - "K" General correspondence, 1942-1966 (Box 3, Folder 121)
    - Karolyi, Catherine, 1957-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 122)
    - Karpiński, Wojciech, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 123)
    - Katarzyna, Sister, 1957-1964 (Box 3, Folder 124)
    - Kister, Hanna, 1947-1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 125)
    - Koszela, Leon, 1947-1958 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Kott, Jan, 1961-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Kowalski, Władysław, 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - Krzemińska, Olga, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - Krzyżanowski, Julian, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - Kuncewiczowa, Maria, 1947-1961 (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - Kunstmann, Heinrich, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 132)
    - Kuryluk, Karol, incoming and outgoing, 1947-1957 (Box 4, Folder 133)
    - Kuźnica, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 134)
    - Kwartalnik Sztuki Współczesnej, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 135)
    - "L" General correspondence, 1949-1965 (Box 4, Folder 136)
    - Landau, Ryszard, 1957-1960, undated (Box 4, Folder 137)
    - Lebenstein, Jan, 1964, undated (Box 4, Folder 138)
    - Lednicki, Wacław, incoming and outgoing, 1964-1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 139-140)
    - Leszczyńska, Aleksandra, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 141)
    - Lewin, Leopold, 1956-1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 142)
    - Lo Gatto, Ettore, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 143)
    - Lyr, Rene, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 144)
    - Łabędź, Leopold, 1962-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 145)
    - "M" General correspondence, 1948-1965 (Box 4, Folder 146)
    - Maliniak, Julian, 1954-1964, undated (Box 4, Folder 147)
    - Mann, Zofia, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 148)
    - Mantel, Feliks, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 149)
    - Markov, V., 1964 (Box 4, Folder 150)
    - Międzyrzecki, Artur and Julia, 1956-1966 (Box 4, Folder 151)
    - Mihaly, Baba, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 152)
    - Mikelberg, Henryk and Maria, 1939-1944 (Box 4, Folder 153)
    - Miłosz, Czesław, incoming and outgoing, 1959-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 154-159)
    - Morris, Ira and Edith, incoming and outgoing, 1948-1962, undated (Box 4, Folder 160-162)
    - Morska, Irena, 1949, undated (Box 5, Folder 163)
    - Mycielski, Zygmunt, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 164)
    - "N" General correspondence, 1947-1958 (Box 5, Folder 165)
    - New-Land Foundation, 1961-1965, undated (Box 5, Folder 166)
    - Nowak, Jan, ougoing, 1963-1966, undated (Box 5, Folder 167)
    - Nowakowski, Tadeusz, 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 168)
    - Nowakowski, Zygmunt, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 169)
    - "O" General correspondence, 1947-1958 (Box 5, Folder 170)
    - "P" General correspondence, 1947-1965 (Box 5, Folder 171)
    - Paczkowska, Irena, 1959-1963 (Box 5, Folder 172)
    - Państwowy Instytut Wydawniczy, incoming and outgoing, 1948-1963 (Box 5, Folder 173-174)
    - Parandowski, Jan, 1946-1956, undated (Box 5, Folder 175)
    - Parnicki, Teodor, 1942-1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 176)
    - PEN Club, 1947-1967 (Box 5, Folder 177-178)
    - Pescetto, Alberto, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 179)
    - Pipes, Richard, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 180)
    - Płomieński, J.E., 1948 (Box 5, Folder 181)
    - Pomianowski, Jerzy, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 182)
    - Przyboś, Bronisława, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 183)
    - "R" General correspondence, 1958-1967 (Box 5, Folder 184)
    - Radio Free Europe, 1963-1967 (Box 5, Folder 185)
    - Radio-Television Francaise, 1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 186)
    - Rappaport, Leon, 1959-1981, undated (Box 5, Folder 187-190)
    - Romanowicz, Kazimierz, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 191)
    - Rudnicki, Adolf, 1948-1962, undated (Box 5, Folder 192)
    - Rudzki, Adam, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 193)
    - "S" General correspondence, 1947-1967 (Box 5, Folder 194)
    - [Sagen, N.?], 1947-1949 (Box 5, Folder 195)
    - Scherer, Olga, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 196)
    - Schiller, Irena, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 197)
    - Segala, Amos, incoming and outgoing, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 198)
    - Sidre, Georges, 1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 199)
    - Sikorska, Jadwiga, 1943-1949 (Box 5, Folder 200)
    - Sikorska, Maria, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 201)
    - Silone, Ignazio, 1956-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 202)
    - Silva Editore, incoming and outgoing, 1960-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 203-210)
    - Skwarczyńska, Stefania, 1947-1948 (Box 6, Folder 211)
    - Śpiewak, Jan, outgoing (copies and transcripts), 1965 (Box 6, Folder 212)
    - Stawar, Edward, 1948-1961 (Box 6, Folder 213)
    - St. Martin's Press, 1960-1962 (Box 6, Folder 214)
    - Stempowski, Jerzy, incoming and outgoing, 1960-1963 (Box 6, Folder 215)
    - Sterlingowa, Halina, 1958-1959, undated (Box 6, Folder 216)
    - Struve, Gleb, 1962-1966, undated (Box 6, Folder 217)
    - Szelburg-Zarembina, Ewa, 1946-1957, undated (Box 6, Folder 218)
    - Szytman, Arnold, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 219)
    - "T" General correspondence, 1948-1964 (Box 6, Folder 220)
    - La table ronde, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 221)
    - Tarski, Maria and Alfred, 1965, undated (Box 6, Folder 222)
    - Temerson, Stefan, 1962-1964 (Box 6, Folder 223)
    - Turowicz, Jerzy, incoming and outgoing, 1947-1963 (Box 6, Folder 224)
    - Tuwim, Julian, 1947, undated (Box 6, Folder 225)
    - Tworczość, 1949-1962 (Box 6, Folder 226)
    - "U" General correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 227)
    - University of California, Berkeley, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 228)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Grampp, Eileen
    - "V" General correspondence, 1960-1967 (Box 6, Folder 229)
    - Vallentin, Antonina, 1949, undated (Box 6, Folder 230)
    - Van Velde, Jacob, 1957-1963 (Box 6, Folder 231)
    - Vercors, Rita and Jean, 1955-1965, undated (Box 6, Folder 232-233)
    - Verdiani, Carlo and Gabriella, 1956-1961, undated (Box 6, Folder 234)
    - Vincenz, Stanisław, 1960-1965 (Box 6, Folder 235)
    - "W" General correspondence, 1945-1963 (Box 6, Folder 236)
    - Walden, Sina, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 237)
    - Wasserman, Harry, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 238)
    - Wat, Andrzej, incoming and outgoing, 1959-1967 (Box 6, Folder 239)
    - Wat, Françoise, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 240)
    - Wat, Paulina, 1942-1960, undated (Box 6, Folder 241-242)
    - Ważyk, Adam, 1945, undated (Box 6, Folder 243)
    - Wegner, Jan, 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 244)
    - Wiadomości, 1962-1967 (Box 6, Folder 245)
    - Wierzyński, Kazimierz, incoming and outgoing, 1959-1964 (Box 6, Folder 246)
    - Wiktor, Jan, 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 247)
    - Wirpsza, Witold, incoming and outgoing, 1963-1967 (Box 6, Folder 248)
    - Wittlin, Józef and Halina, 1947-1966 (Box 6, Folder 249)
    - Wolfe, Robert, outgoing, undated (Box 6, Folder 250)
    - Woroszylski, Wiktor, 1956-1963 (Box 6, Folder 251)
    - Wydawnictwo Literackie, 1956-1963 (Box 6, Folder 252)
    - Wygodski, Irena and Stanisław, 1948-1962 (Box 6, Folder 253)
    - Yale University, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 254)
    - "Z" General correspondence, 1945-1962 (Box 6, Folder 255)
    - Zabłudowski, Tadeusz, 1947, undated (Box 6, Folder 256)
    - Zahorska, Stefania, 1956-1960 (Box 6, Folder 257-259)
    - Zamoyski, Stefan, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 260)
    - Zaremba, Józef, 1959-1961, undated (Box 7, Folder 261)
    - Zaremba, Zygmunt, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 262)
    - Zawiejski, Jerzy, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 263)
    - Żółkiewski, Stefan, 1947-1958, undated (Box 7, Folder 264)
    - Żuławski, Marek, 1957-1963, undated (Box 7, Folder 265)
    - Żuławski, Mirosław, 1956-1960 (Box 7, Folder 266)
    - Związek Pisarzy Polskich na Obczyźnie, 1958-1963 (Box 7, Folder 267)
    - Związek Zawodowy Literatów Polskich, 1946-1958 (Box 7, Folder 268)
    - Unidentified correspondents, incoming and outgoing, 1945-1968 (Box 7, Folder 269-274)
  - Paulina Wat Correspondence
    Some Paulina Wat correspondence, including letters addressed to both Paulina and Aleksander Wat, is interfiled with the Aleksander Wat Correspondence.
    - "B" General correspondence, 1977-1982 (Box 8, Folder 275)
    - Bolecki, Włodzimierz, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 276)
    - Brodsky, Joseph, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 277)
    - Broniszówna, Seweryna, incoming and outgoing, 1963-1981 (Box 8, Folder 278-282)
    - Brzeziński, Zbigniew, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 283)
    - "C" General correspondence, 1978-1983 (Box 8, Folder 284)
    - Ciołkoszowa, Lidia, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 285)
    - Czapski, Józef, 1969-1983 (Box 8, Folder 286)
    - "F" General correspondence, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 287)
    - "G" General correspondence, 1968-1979 (Box 8, Folder 288)
    - Gallant, Mavis, 1965-1979, undated (Box 8, Folder 289-290)
    - Girarden, Marianna, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 291)
    - Goldberg, Jakub, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 292)
    - Gołębiowska, Maria, 1981-1984 (Box 8, Folder 293)
    - Grabska, Halina, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 294)
    - Grynsztejn, Rita, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 295)
    - "I" General correspondence, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 296)
    - Jeleński, Konstanty, 1966-1982 (Box 8, Folder 297)
    - "K" General correspondence, 1946-1978 (Box 8, Folder 298)
    - Kamieńska, Anna, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 299)
    - Karpiński, Wojciech, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 300)
    - Klara, Sister, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 301)
    - Kołakowski, Leszek, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 302)
    - Kossowska, _____, 1977-1981 (Box 9, Folder 303)
    - Kowalczykowa, Alina, 1979-1984 (Box 9, Folder 304)
    - Krzemińska, Olga, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 305)
    - "L" General correspondence, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 306)
    - Lebenstein, Jan, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 307)
    - Lew family, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 308)
    - Lourie, Richard, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 309)
    - "M" General Correspondence, 1948-1965 (Box 9, Folder 310)
    - Micińska, Anna, 1980-1981 (Box 9, Folder 311)
    - Miłosz, Czesław, 1976-1989 (Box 9, Folder 312)
    - Nyczek, Tadeusz, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 313)
    - "O" General Correspondence, 1948-1977 (Box 9, Folder 314)
    - "P" General Correspondence, 1968-1985 (Box 9, Folder 315)
    - Paumritter, Barbara, 1965, undated (Box 9, Folder 316)
    - Pollakówna, Joanna, 1968-1984 (Box 9, Folder 317)
    - "R" General Correspondence, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 318)
    - "S" General Correspondence, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 319)
    - Sikorska, Marija, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 320)
    - Skwarczyńska, Stefania, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 321-322)
    - "T" General Correspondence, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 323)
    - Trznadel, Jacek, 1982-1984 (Box 9, Folder 324)
    - Turowicz, Jerzy, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 325)
    - Ulrich, Lucy, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 326)
    - University of California Press, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 327)
    - Vincenz, Irena, 1969-1974 (Box 9, Folder 328)
    - Vuchic, Rada, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 329)
    - Vujičić, Petar, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 330)
    - "W" General Correspondence, 1965-1978 (Box 9, Folder 331)
    - Wat, Aleksander, 1940s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 332-334)
    - Wat, Andrzej, 1956, undated (Box 10, Folder 335)
    - Wirpsza, Witold and Maria, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 336)
    - Wyka, Marta, 1981-1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 337)
    - Zarembińska, Marysia, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 338)
    - Zaworska, Helena, 1979-1982 (Box 10, Folder 339)
    - Zieliński, Jan, 1981-1983, undated (Box 10, Folder 340)
    - Żuławski, Marek, 1976-1984 (Box 10, Folder 341)
    - Condolences on Aleksander Wat's death, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 342-345)
    - Unidentified family letters, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 346)
    - Unidentified correspondents, 1958-1986 (Box 10, Folder 347-348)
    - Outgoing letters to various correspondents (copies), 19771978 (Box 10, Folder 349)
- Writings, 1942-1982; Series II; 9.59; (24 boxes)
  Series II is organized into five subseries: Major Works of Poetry and Prose, Poetry, Essays, Short Fiction and Playscripts, Memoirs, and Notebooks. The organization of material within each subseries roughly preserves the arrangement in which it was received by the Beinecke Library.